I always say that football is...
我总是说足球是...
I’ve seen everything in football.
我在足球中见过一切
I don’t think I’ve ever seen a ten minutes like that.
我不认为我曾经见过那样的十分钟
My name is Eli Mengem and for the past few years
我叫Eli Mengem 过去几年
I’ve been traversing Europe
我一直在欧洲各地旅行
documenting the tales of football clubs and their fanbases
记录那些足球俱乐部和球迷的故事
who’ve been on the verge of winning something
他们即将赢得一些荣誉
for the first time in a long time.
这是很久以来的第一次…
If not ever.
甚至永远不会
From Northern Turkey
从土耳其北部
to Southern Spain.
到西班牙南部
From South West Germany to the
从德国西南部
Basque country.
到巴斯克地区
I’ve been on a mission to show how important it is
我一直在努力展示一件重要的事
that the game has a variety of winners
这项运动需要不同的获胜者
So that we learn about new places.
这样我们就能了解新的地方
New people.
新的人们
New cultures.
新的文化
And most importantly, new stories.
最重要的是，新的故事
Then came the 2022 FIFA World Cup.
然后是 2022 年 FIFA 世界杯
Where I knew the exact “Once In A Lifetime” story I had to tell.
我清楚地知道我必须讲述的“一生一次”的故事
So as the world’s media descended on Qatar
当全世界的媒体都涌向卡塔尔
to be at the tournament.
报道比赛时
COPA90 and I decided to fly 8000 miles in the opposite direction
COPA90和我决定飞往8000英里外的相反方向
to tell the ultimate story of a football fanbase
去讲述一个足球球迷群体的终极故事
on the brink of ending a 36 year wait
他们即将结束36年的等待
for the biggest prize in sport.
为了赢得这项运动中最大的奖项
But what we found we found was a story that transcended football.
但我们发现的是一个超越足球的故事
A story that reached into the very soul of a nation
一个触及国家灵魂的故事
that laid itself bare over two fateful weeks.
这个国家在决定性的两周里毫无保留地展现了自己
A story that etched a struggle for identity in a search for glory
这是一个关于身份斗争的故事
that began over two centuries ago
始于两个多世纪前的荣耀追寻
A story about Lionel Messi.
一个关于Lionel Messi的故事
Argentina.
关于阿根廷
And 45 million people yearning to reclaim their place in history.
关于4500万人渴望重新夺回他们在历史中的位置
This is the all angle, on the ground, as it happened,
这是全方位，在现场，实时记录的
ultimate account of perhaps the greatest football story of our time.
终极叙述 这或许是我们时代最伟大的足球故事
- Yo Eli what’s going on man, where are we at?
- 嘿Eli 怎么样 我们现在在哪里？
We are in Argentina.
我们在阿根廷
A very hot, a very sweaty Argentina
一个非常炎热，非常潮湿的阿根廷
during their first ever summertime World Cup
在他们有史以来第一个夏季世界杯期间
and I’m excited.
我很兴奋
There’s only a couple of hours before...
只剩下几个小时了…
the big Quarter-Final against the Dutch.
距离四分之一决赛对阵荷兰
We don’t actually have too much to do before we have to be
在我们必须到达预计会爆满的球迷区之前
in what is expected to be a sold out fanzone.
我们其实没有太多事情要做
So first things first we need to find my fixer, Val.
所以首先我们需要找到我的联络人，Val
and then just before the fanzone
然后就在去球迷区之前
I’m going to catch up with a journalist friend of mine, Santi.
我要去见我的一个记者朋友，Santi
Who I think is the perfect person
我认为他是最合适的人
to give me an understanding of
来帮我理解
how big of a deal
这里发生的事情
what’s going on here is
有多么重要
and just what we’re in store for.
以及我们将要面对的是什么
Now tell me, first and foremost
现在告诉我 首先
we could have picked any country to go to
我们可以选择任何一个国家
to cover this World Cup.
去报道这届世界杯
We put all our budget on this one.
我们把所有预算都花在了这里
Why do you think we did it? And was it a good idea?
你觉得我们为什么这么做？这是个好主意吗？
Yes it was a great idea for you to come to Argentina.
是的 你们来阿根廷是个很棒的主意
Because, I mean, these people are longing
因为 这些人渴望
for something to be cheerful about.
一些值得欢呼的事情
This World Cup is like a boiling point...
这届世界杯就像是一个沸点...
for this national team.
对于这支国家队来说
Because, the World Cup is an obsession for Argentines.
因为，世界杯对阿根廷人来说是一种痴迷
It’s already 36 years
已经36年了
that’s how long we’ve been waiting for someone, anyone
这就是我们一直在等待某人，任何人
to make us lift that trophy again.
再次为我们举起那座奖杯
35’ GOAL ARGENTINA! Molina
35分钟 阿根廷进球！Molina
It is now or never.
现在就是机会
It is right at this moment.
就在这一刻
1-0
1-0
To finally, finally...
终于 终于...
get the chance to win the trophy.
有机会赢得奖杯
1 -0 up at the break and with a foot in the Semi-Final
半场结束1-0领先 一只脚已经踏入半决赛
the emotional climate of the fanzone
球迷区的情绪氛围
was a collective, confident ecstasy.
是一种集体的、自信的狂喜
Which was an even more notable achievement
这是一个更加显著的成就
given the actual climate.
考虑到实际的天气情况
You see with this World Cup being the first ever
你看 这届世界杯是历史上第一次
to be played in December.
在12月举行
It meant that Argentina were experiencing
这意味着阿根廷正在经历
their first international tournament in their summer.
他们在夏季的第一次国际比赛
And whilst that had helped create atmospheres and crowds
虽然这帮助创造了冬季赛事中
never quite seen during winter tournaments.
从未见过的氛围和人群
It also brought it’s own obstacles.
但它也带来了自己的挑战
Yet as the second half approached
随着下半场的临近
and the temperature went up another level
气温再次上升
it was clear that no one was going anywhere...
显然没有人愿意离开...
In fact as the temperature went up
事实上 随着气温的上升
so did the atmosphere.
气氛也变得更加热烈
As Argentinians young and old defied their health
阿根廷人无论老少 都无视健康
to show their support.
来展示他们的支持
And then, deep into the second half
然后，进入下半场
their efforts were rewarded.
他们的努力得到了回报
73’ - PENALTY ARGENTINA
73分钟 - 阿根廷获得点球
And so with only 15 minutes left
所以 在比赛仅剩15分钟时
Argentina had a golden chance to double their lead
阿根廷有一个绝佳的机会将领先优势扩大
with a spot kick taken by...
点球由...
Who else?
还能是谁？
Messi who is heading into this World Cup
Messi 他在这届世界杯上
still at the top of his powers but at 35 years old
依然处于巅峰状态 但35岁的年纪
which could mean
可能意味着
this is the last shot he will ever have
这是他最后一次机会
of trying to win the trophy he has been looking for...
去赢得他一直在追寻的奖杯...
basically from the very first moment he put an Argentina shirt on.
自从他第一次穿上阿根廷球衣的那一刻起
2-0 up with a goal and an incredible assist from Messi
2-0领先 Messi贡献了一粒进球和一次不可思议的助攻
Argentina were on their way to the Semi-Finals of a World Cup
阿根廷以童话般的方式
in fairytale fashion.
晋级世界杯半决赛
And so, swept up by the sun and the songs.
于是 在阳光和歌声的包围中
The jumping and the jubilation.
跳跃和欢呼
The hugs
拥抱
and the kisses.
和亲吻
With only ten minutes left it truly felt like we had touched down
比赛仅剩十分钟时 我们真的感觉像是来到了
on the happiest place on earth.
地球上最快乐的地方
However...
然而...
Little did we know what was to come.
我们并不知道接下来会发生什么
Netherlands have scored.
荷兰队进球了
It’s gone from elation to tension...
从狂喜到紧张...
like that.
就在一瞬间
We got six minutes to hold on.
我们还有六分钟要守住
The Dutch just should have scored.
荷兰队刚刚差点进球
Even though they still had a 1 goal lead...
尽管他们仍然领先1球...
And with the referee adding 10 minutes of additional time
随着裁判补时10分钟
That climate of confident ecstasy had evaporated.
那种自信的狂喜氛围已经消散
Argentina have given away a free kick
阿根廷送出了一个任意球
They’ve actually done it.
他们真的做到了
All of a sudden, the happiest place on earth
突然间 地球上最快乐的地方
had become anything but.
变得不再快乐
And if you thought regular time was emotional...
如果你认为常规时间已经足够情绪化...
Are we going to penalties.
我们要进入点球大战了吗？
2-0 up with ten minutes, but it's going down to penalties.
十分钟2-0领先，但现在要进入点球大战了
Ten clear chances in extra time.
加时赛中有十次明显的得分机会
But it's going to penalties.
但还是要靠点球
It's 50/50 if Argentina will prevail.
阿根廷能否胜出 概率是50/50
It's 50/50 if the foothall gods will shine on this very football religious country.
足球之神是否会眷顾这个对足球充满信仰的国家 概率也是50/50
It's 50/50. It's now or never.
50/50的概率 现在就是机会
Despite being only two penalties into the shootout
尽管点球大战只进行了两轮
the extreme passion and emotional attachment
阿根廷人对这场比赛
Argentina places on this game
的极端热情和情感投入
was already on full display.
已经充分展现
And then came the next Dutch penalty...
然后轮到荷兰队的下一个点球...
It’s like they can’t win, easily...
他们似乎无法轻松取胜...
And so after a match that had given us just about everything.
于是 在一场几乎包含了所有元素的比赛之后
Argentina were just one Lautaro Martinez penalty away
阿根廷距离半决赛
from the Semi Finals.
只差Lautaro Martinez的一个点球
We go one step closer!
我们又近了一步！
Finally, after a two and a half hour emotional rollercoaster ride
终于 在经历了两个半小时的情绪过山车之后
that only this country, in this game could go through
只有这个国家 在这场比赛中
Argentina had snuck into the Semi-Final.
阿根廷艰难地闯入了半决赛
And whilst there were cries of happiness
尽管有快乐的呼喊
hugs of relief
如释重负的拥抱
and jumping for joy.
和欢欣雀跃的跳跃
There were also tears.
但也有泪水
Where it was evident the emotional toll
显然 支持这支球队在这届赛事中
of supporting this team in this tournament
所带来的情感压力
was becoming overbearing for some.
对一些人来说已经变得难以承受
Especially knowing there were still two more matches
尤其是知道他们还需要再赢两场比赛
they’d have to overcome
他们必须克服
to finally achieve their World Cup dream
才能最终实现他们的世界杯梦想
for the first time in nearly 40 years.
这是近40年来的第一次
And so as some hung around to hear the words
于是 当一些人留下来聆听
of the man of the match.
全场最佳球员的发言
We left the fan zone as that 37 degree heat wave...
我们离开了球迷区，37度的热浪…
turned into something completely different.
变成了完全不同的天气
And came across local juice vendor Chino.
我们遇到了当地的果汁摊贩Chino
Who, in a sign of the dire economic times of the country
在这个国家严峻的经济形势下
wasn’t able to leave his juice stand to watch the game,
他无法离开他的果汁摊去看比赛
instead, listening to it outside the fan zone on his radio.
只能在球迷区外用收音机收听比赛
I was with an old lady here.
我和一位老太太在这里
And when we heard the goal we both hugged each other.
当我们听到进球时 我们互相拥抱
With that old lady.
和那位老太太
And we both shouted.
我们一起欢呼
And I told hèr: "If they score one more goal...
我对她说：“如果他们再进一球...
I'll eat your mouth!"
我就亲你！”
And so as we headed out to the Obelisco
于是 当我们前往方尖碑时
where we’d been told despite the monsoon like rain conditions
我们被告知，尽管下着暴雨
thousands had already gathered
但已经有数千人聚集在那里
for the traditional post win celebrations.
进行传统的赛后庆祝活动
It was Chino’s poetic words on what this all meant
Chino用诗意的语言解释了这一切的意义
that made sense of it all.
让我们明白了这一切
It is not about Messi or any other player.
这不是关于Messi或任何其他球员
It's about hope.
这是关于希望
The hope of the people.
人民的希望
Half an hour ago we were all like this! Suffering!
半小时前我们还都在受苦！
And in one second, one second...
然后在一瞬间 一瞬间...
the door of happiness opened.
幸福之门打开了
Where no one gives a damn, about anything and nothing...
在那里 没有人关心任何事情...
..it takes you out of one place and puts you in another one.
...它把你从一个地方带到了另一个地方
It's like a dimensional doorway.
就像一扇维度之门
The next morning came with a combination of
第二天早晨 伴随着
jetlag, wet clothes and a hangover.
时差、湿衣服和宿醉的感觉
But mostly a sense of disbelief into what we had just experienced
但更多的是对我们刚刚经历的24小时
only 24 hours into our time in Argentina.
感到难以置信
So to start the day I headed to meet Santi again.
于是 我开始新的一天 再次与Santi见面
Who wore the exact same shirt
他穿着和昨天完全一样的衣服
and insisted we met and did the interview in the exact same place.
并坚持我们在同一个地方见面并做采访
All for one very Argentine phenomenon.
这一切都是为了一个非常阿根廷的现象
I mean, it’s the “Cabalas”
这就是“Cabalas”
Oh ok, the Cabalas, I keep hearing about the “Cabalas”
哦 好的 Cabalas 我一直在听说“Cabalas”
It’s a belief that if you,
这是一种信念 如果你
when you did something and it worked out...
做了某件事并且成功了...
you want to repeat that thing so that
你会想重复那件事 以便
that it might yield the same result.
它能带来同样的结果
I mean look at me for example.
比如看看我
I mean, I need a shave.
我需要刮胡子
I need a haircut.
我需要理发
And I don’t want to do any of those things because
但我不想做这些事 因为
whilst not getting shaved and not getting haircuts
在不刮胡子、不理发的情况下
Argentina have reached this far into this World Cup.
阿根廷已经在这届世界杯中走得很远
But Santi wasn’t the only one affected by the World Cup “Cabalas”
但Santi并不是唯一一个受到世界杯“Cabalas”影响的人
I wear the same shoes. I wake up at the same time.
我穿同样的鞋子 我在同一时间起床
I haven't washed my shirt in a month.
我已经一个月没洗我的衬衫了
We sit in the exact same place
我们在同一个地方坐下
and do the exact same things on matchdays.
并在比赛日做同样的事情
When Argentina plays, we make ʻpicada’.
当阿根廷比赛时 我们会做“picada”
We don't wear a jersey, because in the Copa America that we won
我们不穿球衣 因为在我们赢得美洲杯时
we also didn't do it.
我们也没穿
And as long as Argentina keeps winning, we keep making picada.
只要阿根廷继续赢球 我们就会继续做picada
We use the same chairs in the same order
我们用同样的椅子 按同样的顺序
and we eat the same before every match.
并在每场比赛前吃同样的东西
It's about trying to do the same things you did on the day you won.
这是为了尝试重复你在胜利那天所做的所有事情
From their superstitious behaviour
从他们的迷信行为
to painting their futsal arenas like the Sistine Chapel
到将他们的五人制球场画得像西斯廷教堂一样
it was dawning on me that the Argentinian passion for football
我逐渐意识到 阿根廷人对足球的热情
genuinely bordered on religious fervour.
几乎达到了宗教般的狂热
It's portraying Maradona,
这是描绘Maradona
passing onto Messi...
传递给Messi…
the creation of football.
足球的创造
But, this was only the tip of the iceberg I discovered
但这只是冰山一角 我发现
when it came to Argentine passion for all things football.
阿根廷人对足球的热情无处不在
From Ezequiel Suranyi the founder of Futbolitis,
从Futbolitis的创始人Ezequiel Suranyi
a creative art studio dedicated to the game.
一个致力于足球的创意艺术工作室
It’s not a sport, it goes way beyond.
这不是一项运动 它远远超越了运动
It’s a cultural phenomenon
它是一种文化现象
that affects different lives in different ways.
以不同的方式影响着不同的生活
To the unofficial Museum of El Grafico
到El Grafico的非官方博物馆
built into a tin shed in the countryside
建在乡村的一个铁皮棚里
that’s dedicated to preserving the memory
致力于保存
of the country’s most adored football publication.
该国最受喜爱的足球出版物的记忆
To Carlos Ruiz
再到Carlos Ruiz
a man who turned his passion for sportswear
一个将对运动鞋的热情
into a world famous store
转化为世界知名商店的人
visited by some of the biggest names in the world.
吸引了世界上一些最大牌的球星前来光顾
And whether their passion was expressed through footwear
无论他们的热情是通过鞋子
or photography,
还是摄影来表达
when chatting to them about football
当与他们谈论足球时
there was one subject in particular
有一个话题特别让他们兴奋
that was getting them most excited.
那就是我们拥有世界上最好的球员
We have the best player in the world.
我们拥有世界上最好的球员
Messi, right now, is waking up.
Messi，现在，正在觉醒
Fifth World Cup my friend.
第五届世界杯了，我的朋友
Players usually play three, at the most.
球员通常最多参加三届
And whilst yes, they were gushing about his on pitch performance,
虽然是的，他们对他场上的表现赞不绝口
it was what Messi did off the pitch against one Dutch player
但正是Messi在场外对一位荷兰球员的举动
that had Argentinians most enamoured.
最让阿根廷人着迷
No one ever thought Messi could do that.
没人想到Messi会这么做
THE ‘BOBO’ (DUMMY) COULDN’T DEAL WITH IT
“BOBO”（笨蛋）无法应对
It’s another Messi.
这是另一个Messi
He’s older, he’s wiser.
他更成熟，更聪明
He doesn’t take shit from people.
他不会容忍别人的挑衅
We’ve seen him lash out, we’ve seen him complain,
我们看到他发火，看到他抱怨
we’ve seen him be aggressive.
看到他变得有攻击性
#WHATAREYOULOOKINGATDUMMY
#你在看什么，傻瓜？
But to be straight looking at someone, looking at an opponent.
但直接盯着某人，盯着对手
Telling them: What are you looking at?
告诉他们：你在看什么？
Get out of here! Get out of here!
滚开！滚开！
Just like in ‘86
就像在86年一样
Argentina once again had a leader
阿根廷再次有了一位领袖
who wasn’t afraid to express how he felt.
他不怕表达自己的感受
And within hours they were celebrating it
几小时之内，他们就以各种方式庆祝
in every way they could.
他们尽其所能。
WHAT ARE YOU LOOKING AT DUMMY?
你在看什么，傻瓜？
This is the World Cup legacy in Argentina.
这就是世界杯在阿根廷的遗产
Messi says one line, within days...
Messi说了一句话，几天之内…
it’s on shirts, hats, mugs.
它就出现在衬衫、帽子、杯子上
How did he get this shirt made so quickly?
他是怎么这么快就把这件衬衫做好的？
You know, on Friday when the match was finished
你知道，周五比赛结束后
maybe 20 minutes after there were tops and T-Shirts
大概20分钟后，就已经有上衣和T恤
already on sale.
开始销售了
This is the power of this tournament.
这就是这项赛事的力量
This sport.
这项运动
This player.
这位球员
And if they win it bet you it all sells out.
如果他们赢了，我打赌所有东西都会卖光
Day by day we were watching Argentina’s World Cup hysteria grow
日复一日，我们看着阿根廷的世界杯狂热情绪增长
In more weird and wondrous ways
以更奇怪和更奇妙的方式
Even the chicken nuggets...
甚至连鸡块...
have been World Cup-ified
在阿根廷也被世界杯化了
Every single radio station.
每个广播电台
Every single one
每一个
is playing World Cup.
都在播放世界杯
They thought that they had it sorted...
他们以为他们搞定了…
but they had to sort it through penalties.'
但他们必须通过点球大战来解决
World Cup...
世界杯…
'The Physio Luis Martin says:
'理疗师Luis Martin说：
"The players are playing at a high intensity.”
“球员们正在以高强度比赛。”
World Cup...
世界杯…
A game from their World Cup.'
一场来自他们世界杯的比赛
It’s all World Cup.
全都是世界杯
Whether it’s the walls.
无论是墙上
Whether it’s the radio.
无论是电台
Whether it’s the newspapers.
无论是报纸
Everything is World Cup.
一切都是世界杯
It’d probably harder to not hear the World Cup
可能不听世界杯比听世界杯更难
than hear about the World Cup.
但也许世界杯成为如此热门话题的原因...
But perhaps the reason the World Cup was such a talking point...
但也许世界杯成为如此热门话题的原因…
was because the other Argentine topic of discussion
是因为另一个阿根廷的讨论话题
was so depressing.
太令人沮丧了
So inflation for example it’s a huge, huge issue in Argentina.
比如通货膨胀 这是阿根廷的一个巨大问题
It's impossible for a middle-class Argentinian to have savings.
一个中产阶级的阿根廷人几乎不可能有储蓄
ONLY 9.6% OF ARGENTINIANSCOULD SAVE IN 2022
只有9.6%的阿根廷人可以在2022年存钱
INFLATION AVALANCHE
通货膨胀雪崩
This is a really good indication of the inflation here in Argentina.
这很好地表明了阿根廷的通货膨胀
We keep seeing signs like this missing numbers, because
我们不断看到像这样缺少数字的标志，因为
well, when the price keeps changing that quickly
当价格变化如此之快时
there’s no point just changing it from, I don’t know
不停地改动它没有意义，我不知道
something like, 1200 today to 2,000 next month
比如，今天是1200，下个月是2000
maybe 2,500 the week after who knows.
一周后可能是2500，谁知道呢
They can’t buy houses.
他们买不起房子
They can’t buy cars.
他们买不起汽车
They can’t actually make investments.
他们无法进行投资
Because the money just becomes worth less and less every day?
因为钱每天都在贬值？
Exactly!
没错！
It’s burning in their pockets!
钱在他们的口袋里燃烧！
And so as each day went by...
所以随着时间的推移…
we came across demonstration
我们遇到了游行示威
after demonstration,
一次又一次
after demonstration.
又一次
All focused on the same subject.
都集中在同一个主题上
They've offered us indexes that are bebw inilation!
他们提供的指数低于通货膨胀率!
We've turned them down!
我们拒绝了!
And we've launched anongoing strike
我们发起了持续的罢工
that we are doing all across Argentina!
我们正在阿根廷各地进行!
Yet even amongst the protests
然而，即使在抗议活动中
Diego was present.
Diego也出现了
And even in the economic nadir the country had found itself in
即使在国家经济最低谷
reports coming out of Qatar
来自卡塔尔的报道称
were that no country had taken as many fans to the tournament
没有哪个国家像阿根廷一样有这么多球迷前往赛事现场
And with the country now in the Semi-Finals
随着阿根廷进入半决赛
somehow even more supporters were flying out to Doha.
不知何故，更多的球迷飞往多哈
So of course we headed to the airport to meet them.
所以我们当然要去机场迎接他们
From the young and spontaneous.
从年轻和自发的
We won against the Netherlands and said, "Let's go.”
我们战胜了荷兰队，然后说：“我们走吧。”
We weren't going to go to this World Cup.
我们本来不打算去看这届世界杯
To the old and sentimental.
到年老和多愁善感的
Sure. I'm 60 years old.
当然 我60岁了
This will be my last chance to see Messi.
这将是我最后一次看到Messi的机会
To the just plain crazy.
到纯粹的疯狂
Yes， we sold our car to g
是的 我们卖了车去
For an Argentinian to go to a World Cup,
对于一个阿根廷人来说 去世界杯
It’s not pleasure, it’s business.
不是为了娱乐，而是为了正事
You sold your car?
你们卖了车？
Just to go to Doha, your dad sold his car?
只是为了去多哈，你爸爸卖掉了他的车？
You go there to achieve an objective.
你去那里是为了实现一个目标
Not to have fun.
不是为了玩乐
The thing is， we re all crazy.
问题是 我们都疯了
We want to go encourage our country.
我们想去为我们的国家加油
It was an act of emotion.
这是一种情感的宣泄
Another match day had come round
又一个比赛日到来
and with it, another scorcher.
随之而来的是另一场酷热
This time with the temperature predicted to hit nearly 40 degrees.
这次气温预计将达到近40度
But a heatwave was no match for Argentinians
但热浪无法阻挡阿根廷人
in a World Cup Semi-Final.
对世界杯半决赛的热情
And so with the crowd at the the Buenos Aires fan zone
布宜诺斯艾利斯球迷区的人群
expected to be double the last match.
预计是上一场比赛的两倍
We sent one camera in early to find a space
我们提前派了一台摄像机去占位置
whilst we sent another to roam the streets of Buenos Aires
同时派了另一台在布宜诺斯艾利斯的街头游走
and capture the almost paralysing effect this tournament had
捕捉这场赛事对首都几乎每个角落
on nearly every corner of the capital.
产生的近乎瘫痪的影响
As for me well, since this was a story about Argentina
至于我 既然这是一个关于阿根廷的故事
not just Buenos Aires.
而不仅仅是布宜诺斯艾利斯
I decided to try something a little different.
我决定尝试一些不同的东西
Heading out of the capital and across the country
我离开首都 穿越全国
to see just what the rest of Argentina looks and feels like
去看看阿根廷其他地区在世界杯比赛日的
on a World Cup match day.
样子和感受
And what I found was arguably a more intense sentiment
我发现那里的情感甚至比首都
than even in the capital.
还要强烈
If we don't win now， that's it.
如果我们现在不赢 那就完了
This is our last one， this is the one we must win.
这是我们的最后一次机会 我们必须赢
That's why it has to be now or never.
所以现在就是机会 否则永远没机会了
It's because of Messi， as well. Because he deserves it.
这也是因为Messi 他值得
The world has to gift him the World Cup.
世界应该把世界杯送给他
Because it's unique.
为什么？因为这是独一无二的
Because we're good and we have the players to win this.
因为我们有实力 有球员去赢得这一切
Basically it's now or never!
基本上，现在是关键时刻！
This one is all or nothing!
这是一场孤注一掷的比赛！
And just like the emotional toll
就像赛事对城市中的人们
the tournament was having on those in the city.
带来的情感压力一样
Why don't you watch?
你为什么不看？
To not get nervous.
为了不紧张
I have to take it very easy
我必须保持轻松
because in the last game l almost died.
因为上一场比赛我差点死了
i get anxiety, so l try not to watch and do a bit of work.
我很焦虑，所以我尽量不看，做点工作
And despite being the middle of a Tuesday
尽管这是一个周二的下午
Every town.
每个城镇
Every village.
每个村庄
And everyone was focused on one thing in particular...
每个人都在关注一件事...
And so as the kick off approached
随着开球时间的临近
we jumped back on the highway
我们跳上高速公路
and headed to the city known as the “Cradle of Football”.
前往被称为“足球摇篮”的城市
I’m from Buenos Aires, but when you have to look at
我来自布宜诺斯艾利斯 但当你看到
how they feel football in Rosario.
罗萨里奥人对足球的感受时
I mean, they are crazy about football in there.
我得承认 他们对足球的狂热
I have to admit it.
简直疯狂
Rosario breathes football like no other city in Argentina.
罗萨里奥对足球的热爱 远超阿根廷其他城市
For sure.
毫无疑问
In Rosario they probably take football way too seriously
在罗萨里奥 人们对足球的态度可能过于严肃
Way too heavily.
甚至过于沉重
It gets crazy in there as well.
那里的氛围也非常疯狂
Firstly, it’s the two clubs of Rosario.
首先是罗萨里奥的两支俱乐部
From the moment you enter Rosario
从你进入罗萨里奥的那一刻起
you understand the passion.
你就能感受到这种激情
How deep it goes.
它深入骨髓
The colours are everywhere.
色彩无处不在
Onto every wall.
每一面墙
Every corner.
每一个角落
Every lamp post.
每一根灯柱
It’s all about:
都是关于：
The Red and Black of Newell’s
纽维尔斯老男孩的红与黑
or the Blue and Yellow of Rosario Central.
或罗萨里奥中央的蓝与黄
A level of division.
这种分裂
A level of hate.
这种仇恨
A level of passion.
这种激情
It goes toward a level that is...
达到了一个...
difficult to understand.
难以理解的程度
There’s way too much intensity.
这种强度太过强烈
But maybe that’s what created...
但也许正是这种环境...
Messi.
造就了Messi
You see it was in this cradle of football
正是在这个足球摇篮中
that Messi was born, raised and began his footballing odyssey.
Messi出生、成长并开始了他的足球之旅
Messi’s first club was ‘Grandoli’
Messi的第一家俱乐部是“Grandoli”
a small football club in the South of Rosario.
罗萨里奥南部的一个小足球俱乐部
And so with Messi’s Rosarino football journey
随着Messi在罗萨里奥的足球旅程
starting at Grandoli.
从Grandoli开始
So did ours...
我们的旅程也开始了...
Can we go in?
我们能进去吗？
It’s just mad to think, like
想想真是疯狂
it all started...
这一切都始于...
here.
这里
At Grandoli.
在Grandoli
On that pitch.
在那片球场上
Where he did the same magic he’s been performing
他从五岁起就在这里施展魔法
to 35 now.
到现在35岁
But to sit here, in this kind of...
但坐在这里，在这种…
birthplace, of...
诞生地
what could be the greatest player of all time.
可能是史上最伟大球员的地方
What could almost certainly be
几乎可以肯定的是
if he wins this tournament, in less than a week.
如果他在不到一周的时间内赢得这场比赛
I don’t know, it’s magic.
我不知道 这太神奇了
I could stay here all day and soak it up, but...
我可以在这里待上一整天 沉浸其中 但...
we got kick off against Croatia in about 15 minutes.
我们还有大约15分钟就要对阵克罗地亚了
I’ve been invited to a party...
我被邀请参加一个派对...
That party was being hosted by Farid
那个派对是由Farid举办的
a talented Rosarino photographer I’d seen online.
他是我在网上看到的一位才华横溢的罗萨里奥摄影师
Whose photos in Rosario’s World Cup celebrations
他在罗萨里奥世界杯庆祝活动中的照片
had inspired me to come to the city in the first place.
最初激励我来到这座城市
And so as the streets of Buenos Aires emptied
当布宜诺斯艾利斯的街道空无一人时
and it’s bars, restaurants and fan zones filled to capacity.
酒吧、餐厅和球迷区却挤满了人
We made it to Farid’s just in time
我们及时赶到了Farid的家
to strap ourselves in for another ride
系好安全带，准备再次乘坐
on the emotional rollercoaster that is
支持阿根廷队的世界杯情感过山车
And from the first minute in, it was a bumpy ride.
从第一分钟开始，这就是一段颠簸的旅程
It threw some Argentine hands in the air
它让一些阿根廷人举起了手
and other Argentine hands on heads.
另一些阿根廷人则抱着头
It threw some of us forward.
它让一些人向前倾
It threw some of us back.
让另一些人向后倒
But whoever you were.
但无论你是谁
Wherever you were.
无论你在哪里
No one was immune from the emotional toll.
没有人能免受情感上的损失
Some tried coping with nicotine.
一些人试图用尼古丁来应对
Others with alcohol.
另一些人则用酒精
Some even tried coping with black magic.
有些人甚至试图用黑魔法来应对
And then...
然后…
And so that emotional rollercoaster had come to a screeching halt.
情感过山车突然停了下来
Where the result of Messi’s next kick
Messi的下一脚的结果
would determine where we go next.
将决定我们下一步的方向
12 yards.
12码
1 Kick.
1脚
46 million people.
4600万人
A 36 year wait.
36年的等待
Messi had put Argentina in the lead of a World Cup Semi-Final
Messi让阿根廷在世界杯半决赛中领先
and the fairytale was back on track.
童话又回到了正轨
And whilst I could try and explain what it felt like,
虽然我可以试着解释这种感觉
the faces amongst the celebrations tell it best.
但庆祝活动中的面孔最能说明问题
And before the tears of joy could even dry
在喜悦的泪水还没来得及擦干之前
the kids in the air could even land
在空中的孩子们还没来得及落地
and the kisses could even be delivered...
在亲吻还没来得及送出之前…
Once again, the faces told the story.
再一次，面孔讲述了故事
And 2 - 0 up and now dominating
2-0领先并占据优势
Argentina had a foot firmly in the door of the World Cup Final.
阿根廷已经一只脚迈进了世界杯决赛的大门
And with the post goal ecstasy contagious and Half-Time called.
随着进球后的狂喜蔓延开来，中场休息的哨声响起
The stress and suffering endured in that first half hour
在上半场半小时所承受的压力和痛苦
had been replaced with smiles,
已经被微笑所取代
celebrations,
庆祝
Cinzano,
Cinzano
and singing in the sunshine at Argentina’s first ever
在阳光下歌唱，在阿根廷有史以来的第一次
summertime World Cup.
夏季世界杯
So as the second half approached
所以当下半场临近时
and I prepared for what I thought would be
我准备迎接我认为的
a celebratory 45 minutes
庆祝的45分钟
I found myself in for a rude surprise.
我发现自己遇到了一个意外
As the moment the second half kicked off....
当下半场开始的那一刻....
The mood instantly changed.
气氛瞬间改变了
Something that I’ve noticed throughout the World Cup is that...
我在整个世界杯期间注意到的一件事是…
Even in the way the Argentines cheer on their team,
即使在阿根廷人为他们的球队加油的方式中
it feels like they are suffering.
感觉就像他们在受苦
They are leaving their voice behind.
他们声嘶力竭
They have to be mentally drained.
他们的精神一定很疲惫
They have to be at the...
他们必须处于…
top of intensity because they are suffering.
高度紧张的状态，因为他们在受苦
So that’s how we live football.
这就是我们体验足球的方式
We live football through hardship.
我们通过苦难体验足球
We live football through...
我们通过…
excruciating pain, you know?
难以忍受的痛苦体验足球，你知道吗？
And whether it was the Argentinian style of suffering as support
无论是阿根廷式的痛苦支持方式
or the fact that 2-0 was the same scoreline
还是2-0的比分让他们想起了
they had before they imploded against the Dutch.
对阵荷兰时的崩溃
No one in the fanzone.
球迷区里没有人
No one in the cafes.
咖啡馆里没有人
And certainly no one in Rosario
当然，在罗萨里奥没有人
seemed to remember the happiness of Half Time.
还记得半场时的快乐
Until...
直到…
Messi picked up the ball near the halfway line...
Messi在中线附近拿球…
And he ran with it.
他带着球跑
And he ran with it some more.
他又带着球跑了一会儿
Until he had the ball at the byline.
直到他把球带到底线
And whilst he didn’t pass to Molina...
虽然他没有传球给Molina…
he did pass it to Alvarez.
但他传给了Alvarez
And that’s when Argentina finally let their guard down.
这时阿根廷终于放松了警惕
No longer was anyone worried about the game.
不再有人担心比赛了
In fact no one was even watching it.
事实上，甚至没有人看比赛
And so as the Buenos Aires fan zone turned into a giant dance floor.
所以当布宜诺斯艾利斯的球迷区变成一个巨大的舞池时
The streets of the capital refilled
首都的街道上又挤满了人
with people heading to the Obelisco
人们前往方尖碑
and our watch party turned into a rave...
我们的观赛派对变成了狂欢…
I went outside to get my head around the story that was unfolding.
我走到外面，想理清正在发生的故事
Well I’ve had to take a step outside on the balcony because
我不得不走到阳台外面，因为
as fun as it is in there, it’s a bit overwhelming to be honest.
虽然那里很有趣，但说实话有点让人难以承受
I came up with the idea of telling this story over a year ago.
我在一年多前就想出了讲述这个故事的想法
When I realised it was going to be Argentina’s
当我意识到这将是阿根廷的
first Summer World Cup.
第一个夏季世界杯
When I realised it was their first since Maradona passed
当我意识到这是Maradona去世后的第一个世界杯
and that he was looking down on them for this tournament.
他正在注视着他们的比赛
And when I realised this really was Messi’s last tournament.
当我意识到这真的是Messi的最后一届比赛时
He’s said it surely was...
他说这肯定是…
and he’s played like it surely was.
而且他的表现也证明了这一点
He’s just created an assist so glorious, so beautiful
他刚刚创造了一次如此辉煌、如此美丽的助攻
it’ll go down in the history of this tournament.
它将载入世界杯的史册
And now this country...
而现在这个国家...
to actually try and fathom what happens with this country.
真的很难想象这个国家会发生什么
I don’t know what happens over the next five days to be honest.
说实话 我不知道接下来的五天会发生什么
What happens now Argentina?
阿根廷现在会发生什么？
How do you prepare for this?
你如何为这一切做准备？
How do you enjoy this?
你如何享受这一切？
And if you win this, how do you celebrate this?
如果你赢了 你如何庆祝？
We are in for something special now.
我们将迎来一些特别的事情
I’m telling you, you thought it was crazy now.
我告诉你 你以为现在已经很疯狂了
I feel like we haven’t seen anything yet.
我觉得我们还没看到真正的疯狂
And so we hit the streets
于是我们走上街头
to see how Rosarinos celebrate the World Cup.
看看罗萨里奥人是如何庆祝世界杯的
Where whether on the back of a bike,
无论是在自行车后座
back of a truck,
卡车后座
back of the bus,
公交车后座
or even at the front of it.
甚至是在公交车前
There was only one place you were heading...
你只有一个目的地...
The city’s own version of the Obelisco gathering.
城市的方尖碑集会
Where tens of thousands had congregated,
成千上万的人聚集在那里
many climbing any vantage point possible
许多人爬上任何可能的制高点
to show what it meant.
来表达这意味着什么
Meanwhile at the Obelisco
与此同时 在方尖碑
It had gone to another level.
庆祝活动已经升级
With bikes,
自行车
barbecues
烧烤
and brass bands
和铜管乐队
And so as the celebrations continued
随着庆祝活动持续到深夜和清晨
deep into the night and morning.
一直持续到深夜和清晨
What was most notable to me were the number of young kids
对我来说最引人注目的是有很多小孩
out way past their bed time, partying alongside their parents
过了睡觉时间，和他们的父母一起庆祝
who evidently wanted their kids to experience the same
他们显然希望他们的孩子体验同样的
Argentine euphoria they were able to enjoy three decades earlier.
他们三十年前享受过的阿根廷式狂喜
And so as the drinks ran out
随着酒水耗尽
and we headed back to the capital.
我们回到了首都
All I could think was...
我唯一能想到的是...
How does this get any bigger?
这还能变得更疯狂吗？